<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A reply to the two answers of the new test in a letter to an eminent person of quality.</title>
            <author>Philalethes.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57034</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12818184</idno>
  <idno type="VID">94172</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240961478</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1083</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8455</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12818184</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57034)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94172)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 776:32)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A reply to the two answers of the new test in a letter to an eminent person of quality.</title>
                  <author>Philalethes.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Philalethes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  James II, 1685-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94172:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94172:1"/>
            <p>A REPLY TO THE TWO ANSWERS OF THE NEW TEST.</p>
            <p>In a Letter to an Eminent Person of Quality.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Filii hominum, usque quo gravi Corde ut quid diligitis vanitatem, &amp; quaeritis mendacium.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Psalm. 4.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, MDCLXXXVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:94172:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>HOnest and Impartial Reader, (if thou art so,) I thought it meet to anticipate thy Judgement in a <hi>Preface,</hi> that thou may'st not be surpriz'd to find so many bitter, and harsh Expressions, un-becoming the milde temper of a Christian; And I do assure thee, (what ever Thou, or the world may think of me,) much against my natural <hi>genius,</hi> for <hi>Cogito Cogitationes Pacis;</hi> But by this you see how easily a Man may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchd from his natural Inclinations, by bad Example. It may be the story of the <hi>Nags-head</hi> may more than ordinarily scandalize thee; But know it's a tradition as old as the Church of <hi>England</hi> her self. Thus heing before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand admonish'd, turn confidently over the Leaves, read, and judge as thou pleasest.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94172:2"/>
            <head>A <hi>VINDICATION</hi> of the <hi>NEW TEST</hi> of the <hi>CHURCH</hi> of <hi>ENGLANDS LOYALTY,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving by your Lordships Command, Perus'd the several <hi>Answers</hi> to the <hi>New Test of the Church of England's Loyalty;</hi> a Paper that (as it seems) has put our Reverend Ch. of <hi>Eng</hi> into so great a ferment of heat and passion, that bare <hi>Billings-gate</hi> Language is now too good for <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Papists,</hi> although His Majesty be of that Profession. I shall, in pursuance to your Lordships Commands, give your Lordship briefly my Sense of the Three Papers.</p>
            <p>The sole design and drift of that in-offensive Paper, Intituled the <hi>New Test of the Church of Englands Loyalty,</hi> was as (I humbly conceive) to shew that the Ch. of <hi>Eng.</hi> was not the sole, or only <hi>Loyal Party</hi> of the Nation; Or indeed rather, that <hi>true Loyalty</hi> was not so incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistent with the Doctrine and Practice of the <hi>Dissenters</hi> from her in point of <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Worship,</hi> as she so confidently (but as falsly) pretends: But if there have been at any time failers in point of <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Loyalty</hi> in the <hi>Dissenters,</hi> so there have been now and then in the Ch. of <hi>Eng.</hi> both in her Minority, Meridian, and now in her Declining Age; and this by several undeniable instances to all, (but those who have no foreheads:) The aforesaid Paper clearly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrates, as your Lordship I am sure is sufficiently convinc'd; and indeed, (my Lord) that I may not dissemble my own satisfaction therein, those instances of that <hi>Paper</hi> so far prevail'd with me, (it containing nothing but matter of Fact, faithfully Recorded by <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Historians</hi> themselves) I could not but judge it un-answerable; so indeed I thought those <hi>Answers</hi> to it, being such nauceous, scurrilous, trifling stuff, deserv'd none: But seeing your Lordship judges other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, I shall consider these <hi>Billings gate Answers,</hi> and then submit my sense of them to your Lordships more judicious censure.</p>
            <p>I shall not then disown, but there was in that Paper of the <hi>New Test,</hi> &amp;c. some severe (yet true) reflections on the <hi>Church of England's Loyalty,</hi> yet far short of Doctor <hi>Sh</hi>'s. invectives in his Pulpit, as also in his Printed Sermon, (although false,) which He and the rest of those sort of Hackney-Scriblers of that Communion, do daily throw so liberally on the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> although as yet no abhorrence is
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94172:3"/>declar'd of them by the Grand Jury of His Majesties most Loyal Borough of <hi>Southwark,</hi> as there was upon that innocent Paper of the <hi>New Test, &amp;c.</hi> as also of the <hi>Queries,</hi> Licensed by an Authority far superiour to that of a <hi>Grand Jury</hi> of the Borough of <hi>Southwark;</hi> but that is the old sincere way of Answering of the <hi>Protestant Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> to her Adversaries, when she is pinch'd in matter of Fact, as witness the like <hi>stigma</hi> to Mrs. <hi>Cellier's</hi> Book, because it could not otherwise be refuted, For though the Times be now far different (God be thank'd) from those then when she Writ her Book, yet the Ch. of <hi>England</hi>'s way of Answering when she is gall'd, is still the same, to get some <hi>Grand Jury</hi> (no matter whether it be their Province, or no,) to Vote it a Libel, and her Adversary is then (as she thinks) for ever silent; In the <hi>interim,</hi> (she like <hi>Sampsons</hi> Foxes, with fire-brands at her Tail,) runs up and down the Kingdom with her pestiferous virulent Libels, every where fastening Lies and calumnies upon the Doctrine and Practice of her Fellow-Subjects who are not of her Communion, only to render them odious to the Government; vainly thereby thinking to support her <hi>Nags-head</hi> Grandeur.</p>
            <p>The <hi>New Test</hi> taxes her of acting in her <hi>Infancy,</hi> contrary to what she now so much values her self upon; as the setting up the Lady <hi>Jane Gray</hi> in her opposition to <hi>Queen Mary's</hi> Lawful Title to the Crown; and the Answerer is not so ingenious as that of <hi>Pedius impersius, Fur es ait</hi> Pedio. Pedius <hi>Quid? crimina rasis Librat in Antithetis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What now? doth our Learn'd Author of the first Answer Reply; <hi>but that it was dubious where the Title lay;</hi> as if there was so much to be said on the behalf of the Lady <hi>Jane Gray</hi>'s Title, that it was not easily discernable in those days, (that is, when the <hi>Protestant Church</hi> was in her Minority;) who had the better Title, the Lady <hi>Jane,</hi> or Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> which is as much as to say, it was not easie to judge in the late Times who had the better Title to the Crown, <hi>Oliver Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> or King <hi>Charles</hi> the II.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The <hi>New Test</hi> charges her with the barbarous Murder (under a mock form of Justice) of Queen <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> (our Gracious Sovereign<hi>'s</hi> Great Grand-mother,) without ever as yet shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any resentment of that horrid Fact, by any one of her Members in Print; to this our Loyal Church of <hi>Englands</hi> Answerer, vouchsafes to give us no other Reply, but bare-fac'd, to own, and justifie the Fact, by insinuating, that she was a Subject to Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and deservedly suffer'd for Treason.</p>
            <p>The Author of the Second <hi>Answer</hi> (after he had saluted the whole body of the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> by those mild and modest appellations
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94172:3"/>of the <hi>Calves of the Hinde,</hi> &amp;c. gives us to understand, that the Ch. of <hi>England is to be understood under a two-fold capacity; first purely,</hi> as <hi>States-men, abstracting from this or that Communion of Christians;</hi> which is as much as to say, the Ch. of <hi>Eng. is not always bound</hi> (according to the Ch. of <hi>England casuistry</hi>) in <hi>her publick Councils,</hi> to <hi>act as Christians or always to follow the Dictates of Conscience and Honour; but may, and ought sometimes</hi> (<hi>as often as the Exigence of State for the support of the Mother-Church of</hi> England <hi>requires,</hi>) <hi>to act sometimes the</hi> Matchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilian, <hi>and sometimes the</hi> Christian. These are his words, <hi>Page</hi> 5. <hi>continually Plotting</hi> (he means the <hi>English Catholicks,</hi>) against her Life and Dignity, and setting up the Queen of <hi>Scots</hi> Title against her, forc'd the <hi>Queen, and her Council</hi> (of which I am sure, some were of the Dignify'd Clergy,) <hi>(which it had not been necessary, I am sure the Members of our Church would have thought it most inhumane) to take away the Life of that unfortunate Princess.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now pray my Lord, would not <hi>Caiphas</hi> his <hi>Expedit Hominem mori ne tota gens pereat,</hi> seem as well to have justify'd the <hi>Jews</hi> Crucifixion of our Blessed Saviour, as our Learn'd Author's pretended necessity to justifie that barbarous and unparallel'd Murder of the most Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, and Absolute, (as Independant of any Power on Earth,) Princess <hi>Mary Queen</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> who was Born, and Dy'd with a better Title to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> than that so much magnify'd <hi>Protestant</hi> Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who put her to Death: But the then Earl of <hi>Kent,</hi> who was one of the Commissioners (and most eager in the Prosecution of her, to see that Fatal Sentence) Decreed in a Church of <hi>Englands</hi> Privy Council, confirm'd also by the Authority of a Ch. of <hi>England</hi> Parliament, (where, and no doubt there were Lords Spiritual con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring in their Votes, as well as Lords Temporal, as they were Voting up <hi>Oates</hi> his <hi>Ʋtopian Plot,</hi>) Executed on that Pious and Saint-like Queen; understood well, the necessity of putting that Queen to Death, when he had told her plainly in these words. <hi>Your Life will be the Death, and your Death will be the Life of our Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if this worthy Author would be but Ingenious, he could not but own, there was no other true necessity of putting this <hi>Sovereign Princess</hi> to Death, but that which the Earl of <hi>Kent</hi> did there express; but her being a <hi>Papist,</hi> and Lawful Heir to the Crown, and that this was consonant to the Maxim of the Ch. of <hi>England</hi> in its <hi>infancy,</hi> appear'd by the proceedings of our Church of <hi>Englands</hi> first Prelate, Arch-bishop <hi>Cranmer,</hi> who, after solemnly having taken his Oath to <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. on his Death-bed, that he would be true to his Will; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after <hi>Edward</hi> the VI's. Death, did by himself, and Bishop
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94172:4"/>
               <hi>Ridley,</hi> influence and comm<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>tate <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>dley</hi> Duke of <hi>Northumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to raise an Army to oppose Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s coming to the Crown, and Proclaim the Lady <hi>Jan<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> which accordingly was done, and all in favour of the Ch. of <hi>England</hi> who was but just then fledg'd with Sacriledge, Rapines, and Spoil of the true <hi>Catholick Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But rather than <hi>Rebellion, Murder, Sanguinary Laws</hi> Enacted by a Ch of <hi>England</hi> Parliament, made against God Almighty's Priests, should want an Apology, our Learn'd Author tells us.</p>
            <p>First, They were meer Acts of State, and the Ch. of <hi>Eng.</hi> may in some cases divest her self of the Christian, to act the pure Politician, especially when she apprehends a <hi>Caiphas</hi>'s <hi>Expedit,</hi> or an absolute necessity, such as was in the fore-mention'd Case of Queen <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the apprehension of the then Earl of <hi>Kent,</hi> (as I said before;) <hi>Your Life will be the Death,</hi> and <hi>your Death will be the Life of our Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, He tells us in the Fifth Page of the Second Answer, that as to the <hi>Sanguinary Laws</hi> made against <hi>Priests,</hi> they <hi>were not made or consented to by the</hi> Convocation, <hi>nor were they ever made Canons of their</hi> Church, as if the Ch of <hi>Eng.</hi> was not then in Being: But when some few of the <hi>Nags-head</hi> Gent. are met forsooth in <hi>Convocation,</hi> (and yet their <hi>Edicts</hi> and <hi>Canons</hi> need the Confirmation of <hi>Lay-Authority,</hi> before they can pass for currant Coyn,) or that their Voting these <hi>San uinary Laws</hi> in the House of Lords, by all the <hi>Bishops,</hi> was insignificant to the charging of them with making of those Barbarous <hi>Savage Laws,</hi> because not Enacted in their <hi>Convocation,</hi> or by their <hi>Convocation</hi> made <hi>Canons</hi> of their <hi>Church;</hi> which Answer seems to me like one of our <hi>Dear Joys Witticisms;</hi> (to return upon this Gent. in his own Dialect) and yet in the Seventh Page of the Second <hi>Answer,</hi> our <hi>Convocation</hi> Gent. seems to approve them, (though not made or consented to by the <hi>Convocation</hi>) by comparing all those against whom they were made, to devouring <hi>Weesles, Hawks, Owls, Buzzards,</hi> and <hi>carrion Crows,</hi> (you see <hi>my Lord,</hi> on whom the spirit of meekness doth rest;) themselves to tame innocent Pidgeons.</p>
            <p>Who would not now nauceate this insipid Scribler, to prove that <hi>Dudley</hi> Duke of <hi>Northumberland</hi> (was not of the Communion of the Ch. of <hi>Eng.</hi> when he rais'd the Rebellion against Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> gives us no other reason, than because, when taken, he offer'd (to save his Life) to embrace the Communion of the Church of <hi>Rome; so true a Son of our Church he was,</hi> (says this nauceous trifler.)</p>
            <p>O! wonderful sly insinuations! Pray did not <hi>Cranmer</hi> your first Ch. of <hi>Eng.</hi> Arch-bishop do the same? if the Queen would have spar'd
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94172:4"/>his Life, which he had forfeited to the Law for High Treason; and yet I am confident he was never the less Ch. of <hi>Eng.</hi> Man, (and ever so re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted by the then Ch. of <hi>Eng.</hi> when he was in Rebellion against his Lawful Soveraign Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> and I pray God to preserve every Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Ch of <hi>England</hi> in their Duty and Allegiance to their Prince when of a different Religion,) for otherwise, if once obnoxious to the Law for Treason, and taken, I fear (if by that trick they can save their lives) they will not much scruple to follow their Archbishop <hi>Cranmers</hi> Example, in offering <hi>to embrace</hi> (as this Pamphleteer hath it,) the <hi>Communion</hi> of the <hi>Church of</hi> Rome. For it is too well known, that of Three Thousand and upwards of Benefic'd Parsons of the strict Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline of the Ch. of <hi>Eng.</hi> when those unhappy troubles began in King <hi>Charles</hi> the I<hi>'s.</hi> Reign, there was very few more then Three Hundred who refus'd to comply with those ungodly times, in Praying and Preaching up the Cause; (the Cant of those days) against their lawful Soveraign; For it is observ'd that of all Sects of Christianity, the Ch. of <hi>England</hi> find themselves most uneasy in Persecution, and do least of all affect Martyrdom.</p>
            <p>I shall only give one instance more of the Ch. of <hi>England</hi>'s <hi>Loyalty</hi> towards a Prince of another Belief, and that shall be in Dr. <hi>Ridley,</hi> first Bishop of <hi>Rochester,</hi> then of <hi>London,</hi> and Canoniz'd by <hi>John Fox</hi> a Ch. of <hi>Eng.</hi> Martyr, (and put in his Calendar with <hi>Red Letters</hi> for the 19th. of <hi>October</hi> as such,) although executed for Treason, (as appears by the Acts and Registers of those times,) for joyning with <hi>Cranmer</hi> in that notable, wicked and barbarous Conspiracy, and Treason, for the Extirpation of all King <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII<hi>'s.</hi> Children, but especially by that pestiferous <hi>Sermon</hi> made by him at <hi>Pauls Cross,</hi> upon the 16th. of <hi>July,</hi> 1553. after King <hi>Edwards</hi> Death, of which <hi>John Stow</hi> Writes thus; <hi>The</hi> 16th. <hi>of</hi> July <hi>being</hi> Sunday, <hi>Doctor</hi> Ridley <hi>Bishop of</hi> London, <note>PLACE="marg" <hi>Stow</hi> An. 1553. Page 1035.</note>
               <hi>by the Command of the Council Preach'd at</hi> Pauls, <hi>where he vehemently perswaded the people in the Title of the Lady</hi> Jane, <hi>and inveighed earnestly against the Title of the Lady</hi> Mary, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He also, (with <hi>Cranmer</hi>) influenc'd the Rebellion of <hi>Wyat;</hi> But for these, and the like peccadilloes of the Ch of <hi>Eng.</hi> against Q. <hi>Mary,</hi> and rather than Queen <hi>Bess</hi> should want an Advocate, our <hi>Convocation-man</hi> has always a ready Answer, that these were no <hi>Convocation Acts,</hi> (still confining the Ch. of <hi>Eng</hi> to her <hi>Convocation,</hi>) as if any thing that was acted by her to the scandal of her neighbours, and had not the ratification of this infallible <hi>tripos,</hi> was to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted altogether foreign to the Ch. of <hi>England</hi> as no way concern'd in those extravagant actions, or ever made <hi>Canons</hi> of their <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:94172:5"/>
            <p> Secondly, by endeavouring in <hi>Page</hi> 4. to invalidate Queen <hi>Mary</hi> a Title to the Crown, as born of an incestuous bed, justifying <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII<hi>'s.</hi> insatiable Luxury, which, and which only Midwiv'd the <hi>Prot. Rel.</hi> into the World, and gave occasion for that thread-bare Scoma, the <hi>Prot. Rel. came out of</hi> Harry <hi>the</hi> VIII's <hi>Codpiece;</hi> and justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Queen <hi>Elizab's.</hi> Title with the most impudent lies that ever were yet heard; And I am confident future Ages will blush, as well as this present, I am sure does, to think that there should be a Ch. of <hi>Eng.</hi> Man so brasen-fac'd to broach such impudent Assertions knowingly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as witness the Records and Histories of those times: But, I find, that by the same way the Ch. of <hi>Eng</hi>'s. Doctrine came amongst us, by the same Artifice it must be Propagated; but God I hope, in his due time, will detect them, and their little <hi>Convocation Forgeries,</hi> that the meanest Capacity of this Nation shall no longer be Impos'd upon at this rate. He tells us then, <hi>that Queen</hi> Elizabeth <hi>was born in Wedlock after a most solemn Divorce, grounded upon one of the justest causes that could be</hi> (the <hi>Ch.</hi> of <hi>Eng.</hi> (and an unlawful Pruritus. This Gent. I warrant you knows where,) <hi>viz. the nullity of his former Marriage with the Lady</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therine <hi>of</hi> Spain (thought so at first,) <hi>by Cardinal</hi> Wolsey, (the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptest and most ambitious States-man, and as shamelesly debauch'd Church-man, wholly addicted to carnal pleasures, and slavishly obse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quious to his Master<hi>'s</hi> King <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII.) <hi>nay by the Pope himself, who, had he not been over-aw'd by the Emperour, would have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd the Marriage lawful; Nay,</hi> (says this well-read Gent.) <hi>did not he sign a Bull to that purpose?) I dare appeal to this Gent. himself,</hi> (says he) <hi>whether there be not a far more Reason to believe it unlawful, for a Man to Marry his Brothers Wife, then there is to think it lawful?</hi> (Truly I am of his mind, if carnally known by the Brother before his Death;) if otherwise, I must crave leave to dissent from this Learned Gent.) <hi>Now if this</hi> Question <hi>must be determin'd in the Affirmitive, does it n<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t directly follow, that Queen</hi> Mary<hi>'s Legitimacy was more uncertain, and consequently her Title did far more need a prop to support the weakness of it, than her Sister Queen</hi> Elizabeth<hi>'s did:</hi> Henry <hi>the</hi> VIII. <hi>her Father knew this well enough, and therefore settled the matter as well as he could</hi> (as well as the Ch. of <hi>Eng.</hi> was,) <hi>by Acts of Parlament, which Right</hi> (says he) <hi>I shall not dispute,</hi> (no I hope not, for if those Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament be once again call'd in question, I know full well what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes of the Ch. of <hi>Eng.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus does this Gent. argue who could now, (considering the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of this Gent. refrain from exclaiming here with <hi>Juvenal, Difficile est Satyram non scribere;</hi> for why should this Gent. think his <hi>ipse dixit</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:94172:5"/>is sufficient to pawm these Forgeries upon Mankind; is it not suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently known how, and on what motives that Divorce was first manag'd, or on what occasion that Conscientious Prince began to have his first scruples concerning his former Marriage, (who as our own <hi>Protestant Historians</hi> testifie,) <hi>never spar'd Woman in his Lust, or Man in his Fury:</hi> The story in short is thus:</p>
            <p>Henry <hi>the</hi> VII. <hi>having begot on the Body of his Queen two Sons,</hi> Arthur <hi>and</hi> Henry; <hi>Prince</hi> Arthur <hi>at the Age of</hi> 14 <hi>years and two Months, was Marry'd to</hi> Catherine <hi>the Daughter of</hi> Ferdinand <hi>King of</hi> Spain: <hi>Now this was done in</hi> November, <hi>and in</hi> April <hi>following, our new Royal Spouse departed this life;</hi> Henry the VII. <hi>being unwilling that so much money, (as he was yearly to pay her for her Dowry,) should go out of the Kingdom of</hi> England <hi>into</hi> Spain; <hi>Married her,</hi> (<hi>by the Permission of Pope</hi> Julius) <hi>to his Second Son; who aster co-habiting with his Queen</hi> 20 <hi>years, and having issue by her, pretends at last to scruple his Marriage to that virtuous Princess, occasion'd by his debauch'd Affections to</hi> Anna Bullen; <hi>now some of his Favourites being infected with the</hi> Lutheran <hi>Heresie,</hi> (which about that time got footing in <hi>England,</hi>) <hi>and affecting Novelties, and change, as well in State, as Religi<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n; observing the Kings Amours and Carresses towards</hi> Ann Bullen, <hi>and his cool and indifferent carriage towards his virtuous Queen, did by sly Insinuations and Arguments, seem to confirm him in his pretended scruples, hoping thereby (in case the Pope would not gratify his beastly Passions) to make him fall out with that See, and introduce a change in</hi> Religion, <hi>as well as in</hi> State; (which had its desir'd effect:) <hi>For accordingly, forthwith under the greatest shew of Holiness and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion imaginable, he inform'd Pope</hi> Clement (who was then Pope) <hi>of his scruple; who by advice of the Conclave, deputed Cardinal</hi> Campegius <hi>into</hi> England <hi>to hear the Cause; and joyning</hi> Cardinal Wolsey <hi>with him in Commission, both men of extraordinary parts:</hi> I could wish they had been of as much integrity, and that they had been but half as zealous to serve God (as Cardinal <hi>Wolsey</hi> said of himself, when he fell into dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace with the King,) as they were to serve that sensual Prince.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In fine, after Cardinal</hi> Campegius <hi>was come into</hi> England, <hi>the King applies himself to him, telling him how unfortunate he was, having the most virtuous Princess in the World for his Wife, should (now after Twenty years co-habitation with her) be troubled at last with scruples, as to the lawfulness of his Marriage with his Brothers Relict, occasion'd (as he said) by the</hi> French <hi>Kings raising some doubts about the Legitimation of his Daughter</hi> Mary, <hi>when he Treated about Marrying her with the Duke of</hi> Orleance; <hi>From that time, he said he could not rest, (or believ'd he ever should,) until his Holiness should rid him of that scruple: However,</hi> (said he) <hi>be the issue what it will, he was resolv'd to submit to the Sentence of his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94172:6"/>Holiness</hi>'s <hi>Delegates, provided the Sentence be just;</hi> (that is, you may be sure, in favour of a new Marriage already design'd with <hi>Anna Bullen;</hi>) <hi>And therefore hop'd they would not give ear to foolish stories and rumours, (for he perceiv'd the people began to smell his design, and already to talk pretty freely of his Amours with</hi> Anna Bullen.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>After this Harangue, the Cardinal repair'd to the Queen, Citing her to his Court; she answer'd but little; Than, that Pope</hi> Julius, <hi>her Father</hi> Ferdinand, <hi>and</hi> Henry <hi>the</hi> VII. <hi>had sufficiently consider'd this difficulty; and had had the opinion of most of the famous Prelates and Divines</hi> (whether consider'd for Piety or Learning) <hi>of the Christian World, before she was Marry'd to the King; As for her part she bore too great defference to the</hi> Catholick Church, <hi>to refuse to submit to her Sentence; And therefore for her Advocates, chooses</hi> Warham, <hi>Arch-bishop of</hi> Canterbury; West, <hi>Bishop of</hi> Ely; Fisher, <hi>Bishop of</hi> Rochester; <hi>the Bishop of</hi> S. Asaph, <hi>with several other Professors of Divinity, and Canon, and civil Law: To be short, after long altercations with the Kings Council, the Queens Advocates alledging the want of Age, and health in Prince</hi> Arthur <hi>to know his Wife; Besides the Queen appeal'd to his own Conscience, whether she came not a pure Virgin to his bed: Yet the Kings Passions growing more unruly, and the flatterers of the King in his Passions, increasing, with the corruption of those times, forc'd the poor Queen (even by the private advice of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legates themselves,) to appeal to</hi> Rome, <hi>where the Pope having a true state of the posture of Affairs in</hi> England, <hi>re-calls</hi> Campegius, <hi>and takes cognisance of the Cause himself: This put</hi> Henry <hi>the</hi> VIII. <hi>into so great a fury, that (what he had long before resolv'd on,) in</hi> November <hi>following he privately Marries</hi> Anna Bullen <hi>(which was to few known before she was perceiv'd to be with Child,) and in</hi> April <hi>following by Proclamation, was declar'd Queen of</hi> England, <hi>and the former Marriage void, and that none hereafter should call Queen</hi> Catherine Henry <hi>the</hi> VIII<hi>'s. Wife, but Prince</hi> Arthurs <hi>Widow. This hast'ned the Sentence of the Pope;</hi> (having maturely debated the Case, with the best and ablest Divines of Christendom,) <hi>in favour of Queen</hi> Catherine;) <hi>which put the King into such a passion, that presently he exterminates the Popes Authority in</hi> England, <hi>and as many as acknowledg'd it, or refus'd to approve of the Second Marriage, to be hang'd, drawd and quarter'd;</hi> (the first steps made toward the Church of <hi>Englands</hi> Religion.) <hi>The Pope, after several Pious (though fruitless Admonitions) Excommunicates him.</hi> This is all the Bull (that ever I Read of.) the Pope was ever dispos'd to send him in favour of the Second Marriage.</p>
            <p>This is a true Narrative (Collected out of the best Historians of those times,) of that business. You see now my Lord, the sincerity as well
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94172:6"/>as impudence of this Scribler; <hi>The just Cause</hi> (as our Author hath it) <hi>of the solemn Divorce,</hi> (viz. <hi>the Kings inconstancy or brutal Passion for</hi> Anna Bullen,) <hi>the Bull that the</hi> Pope <hi>was to sign</hi> (as he tells us,) <hi>to have determin'd the former Marriage unlawful,</hi> (viz Excommunication on the King, and afterwards by succeeding Popes on his spurious Race, by <hi>A. Bullen;</hi>) But I see this Author takes a great deal of satisfaction in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, that he is born without a forehead, for then he thinks he may write any thing, and be as little thoughtful whether he be believ'd, or no.</p>
            <p>However, (to do the Church of <hi>England</hi> right,) I think he is the first Church of <hi>England</hi>-man who ever preferr'd Queen <hi>Eliz</hi>'s. Title to Qu. <hi>Mary</hi>'s. or that ever alledg'd that Qu. <hi>Mary needed a prop to support the weakness of it:</hi> I am sure her Father thought otherwise, when in his Will he order'd her Succession before Q <hi>Eliz.</hi> (notwithstanding the great passion he had for her Mother;) and indeed there are but few <hi>Protestants,</hi> who when they write or speak of her Mother, give her any other Title than that of <hi>Anna Bullen.</hi> So much more Modesty and Candor have the generality of <hi>Protestants,</hi> than this <hi>Convocation Scribler</hi> hath in his foolish Answer; and yet after all, he thinks (I warrant you,) he hath shown so much cunning in his Answer, that he doubts not, but amongst the perpetually mistaken <hi>Mobilee,</hi> he may have the same <hi>Encomium,</hi> that the unthinking Rabble in <hi>Persius</hi>'s time, gave of <hi>Pedio's</hi> defence to his Accusation.</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <l>—Doctas posuisse Figuras.</l>
                  <l>Laudatur. —</l>
               </q> Says the Poet:</p>
            <p>I have one thing more material to consider, (and then I have done,) which is in page 5, of the first Answer, and the only thing (in both) that looks like an Answer, although grounded on a mistake; For the <hi>New Test</hi> does not deny, but that a <hi>Catholick Parliament was then sitting at Q.</hi> Mary<hi>'s Death; nay, that Q.</hi> Eliz. <hi>her self (during Q.</hi> Mary<hi>'s Reign</hi>) <hi>was also a</hi> Catholick, <hi>(at least in outward appearance;) and so indeed,</hi> (as the Answerer hath well observ'd) <hi>could not be rais'd to the Crown by a</hi> Protestant Parliament But though Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> in outward appearance was a <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> when she came to the Crown; yet finding her self now in Power, she daily discover'd her Inclinations towards the Ch. of <hi>Eng.</hi> Religion; and <hi>knowing the weakness of her Title in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parison with that of Q.</hi> Mary <hi>of</hi> Scotland, <hi>rais'd this prelatick Protestancy</hi> call'd the Ch. of <hi>Eng. as a prop to support the weakness of her Title:</hi> This is the sense of what that Paper objects to the Ch. of <hi>Eng.</hi> and whereas in page 5. of the same Answer, he hath these words, <hi>Behold here an
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94172:7"/>incomparable sort of Loyalty, to set up the Title of a B—d, and murder the Legitimate Heir:</hi> It means no more than the horrible practice of the Ch. of <hi>Eng.</hi> of those days, who, knowing full well the weakness of Q <hi>Eliz.</hi> Title, as the justice of Q. <hi>M.</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> influenc'd Q <hi>E.</hi> by their new Ch. of <hi>England's</hi> casuistry, to raise and foment a Rebellion in <hi>Scotland,</hi> against Q. <hi>Mary</hi> their lawful Sovereign, and then to invite her into <hi>England,</hi> (to shun the rage of her Rebellious Subjects,) and there force her to renounce her Title to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> (which was her undoubted right,) during the Life of Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> But not being content with that, they never ceas'd till they had depriv'd her of her Life, for no other reason, but that of the <hi>Exclusioners,</hi> because no <hi>Papist</hi> should Succeed to the Crown) as they had before forc'd her to divest her self of her Right: In fine, the story in short is thus:</p>
            <p>
               <q>After Q <hi>Mary's</hi> Death a <hi>Catholick Parliament</hi> then sitting, where the <hi>Spanish</hi> Faction being most prevalent, meerly out of a Reason of State, when oftentimes the greater Party Ou<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>-votes the better, (<hi>as appears by the</hi> Exclusioners <hi>in the late Parliament,</hi>) considering <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII<hi>'s.</hi> Will, and in opposition to <hi>France,</hi> the next Lawful Heir being then Marry'd to the <hi>Dauphin</hi> of <hi>France;</hi> and fearing that at the same time <hi>England</hi> might become a Province to <hi>France,</hi> did raise this illegitimate Princess to the Crown, who was then in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance a <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> and so by consequence gave no jealousie to the Parliament of any change in Religion: But as soon as she found her self a Crown'd Head; she presently (considering with her self,) that if the Power of the <hi>Spanish</hi> Faction should de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline in <hi>England,</hi> or think fit to take other measures in her Councils; the weakness of her Title might be question'd, <hi>(which soon after hap<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en'd,)</hi> turn'd her self a <hi>Protestant,</hi> and immediately rais'd this Prelatick Protestancy, called the Ch. of <hi>Eng.</hi> (<hi>as the</hi> New Test <hi>hath it,</hi>) as a prop to support the weakness of her Title; and they mutually suggested to those pernicious Councils, (<hi>as a</hi> prop also to support their Infant Church) by wiles and tricks to force that incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Queen <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to Renounce her Lawful Right to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> (during Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> Life,) and then afterwards to Murder her; that the growth of <hi>Protestant Religion</hi> might not be obstructed by a <hi>Popish Successor. This last it is that the</hi> New Test <hi>charges upon the Ch. of</hi> Eng. and not the raising of her to the Crown, which the <hi>Catholicks</hi> are not so dis-ingenious to deny, was done by the <hi>Spanish</hi> Faction of an <hi>English</hi> Catholick Parliament, though that Faction foon after, (though too late,) perceiv'd they should not find their account in it. So true it is that of <hi>Seneca Concilium malum
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94172:7"/>consùltori Pessimum,</hi> and the <hi>Scylla</hi> they thought to shun, (by raising that Illegitimate Lady to the Crown) they soon after split upon; For Q. <hi>E.</hi> nourishing the hopes of the young Duke <hi>Alonson,</hi> that he should be her Husband, wrought <hi>France</hi> into a strict League of Friendship and Amity with her, (so that now she thought her self secure against the secret matchinations of her enemies (both at home and abroad,) put the <hi>Spaniard</hi> upon that memorable (though suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessless Invasion of 88.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus my Lord, your Lordship hath the true account, and reason of raising Queen <hi>El.</hi> to the Crown, which yet nevertheless is not approv'd of by the <hi>Catholicks,</hi> but only shews, that no sort of Men, let them be of what perswasions they will, can plead exemption from all humane infirmities; neither ought personal errours (of some few) to be thrown upon the Doctrine, and practice of the whole Church of which they are Members; And if the Ch. of <hi>Eng.</hi> Scriblers, had been so candid as to have acknowledg'd this Truth, there needed not have been this Reply; for we know the Bishop is yet living, who made <hi>Oates</hi> (for his <hi>Ʋtopian Plot</hi>) his Chaplain of Honour, Authorising him to wear the Scarf, the usual <hi>insigne</hi> of a Doctor; Another Prelate is also living, who shut up the dores and windows of his House against the Duke of <hi>York</hi> when in his journey into <hi>Scotland,</hi> he was to pass by it; A third is also living, who deny'd <hi>Berry</hi> the Sacrament (in <hi>Newgate</hi>) when he was to be Executed, (because Sir <hi>Edmund Bury Godfrey</hi> had <hi>kill'd himself,</hi>) and he would not Damn himself, by owning that he had kill'd him, and acknowledge himself to be privy to <hi>Oates</hi>'s Plot, of which, he knew, and believ'd as little as he himself did; A fourth, <hi>Bish.</hi> also there was, (though since dead) who (when <hi>Oates</hi> had accus'd one <hi>Preston,</hi> a Married Man, before the House of Lords, that he had been his Ghostly Father,) in a rapture of joy, to consider how the Church of <hi>England</hi> should flourish by these lies, came and publickly kiss'd, and hugg'd <hi>Oates;</hi> Nay, we know when their whole Bench Voted the <hi>Catholick</hi> Lords out of the House, and for no other reason, but because the <hi>Catholick</hi> Lords Voted Them in, (O rare example of Gratitude!) and because his Majesty should have fewer friends in that House upon a pinch; And yet God forbid that these, and the like personal failings, should be laid upon the whole diffusive Church of <hi>England,</hi> (so universally spread over the face of the whole Earth;) no, God forbid.</p>
            <p>My Lord, I shall only now sum up all the matter of Fact contain'd in the <hi>New Test,</hi> leaving it to any Impartial judgement, whether these <hi>Two Gentlemen</hi> have given them an adequate <hi>Answer:</hi> The <hi>New Test</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:94172:8"/>tells the Ch. of <hi>Eng.</hi> first, <hi>that she must not appropriate to her self</hi> (alone) <hi>trus Loyalty,</hi> which is certainly true, for the <hi>Papists,</hi> and others come in for a share with them; Secondly, that most of the Members of the Church of <hi>England</hi> have been <hi>Loyal.</hi> That (as God would have it these Two Gentlemen seem to allow of; but then by return of their ingenuity) they will allow none of the Communion of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to have been so, (if acting according to the Principles of that Religion,) and then instances in a fabulous story of <hi>Du Moulin,</hi> (as like that of <hi>Lucians vera Historia,</hi> as one Apple ever was like to another) as that of <hi>the Jesuit throwing up his Cap on the Scaffold for joy when K.</hi> Charles <hi>the</hi> I <hi>was Beheaded;</hi> this Fable he thought would get credit amongst the Rabble, and serve for an <hi>Answer,</hi> as often as the <hi>Catholicks</hi> tell the Church of <hi>England,</hi> how the Dean of <hi>Peterborough</hi> at the Execution of Q. <hi>M.</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> who, after the Hang-man (in a Ch. of <hi>England</hi> zeal,) repeated these words (the usual Cant of those days,) <hi>Long live Q</hi> Elizabeth, <hi>and so let the enemies of the Gospel perish.</hi> Thirdly, he objects to the Ch of <hi>Eng. that the endeavo. ring to force an universal Conformity to her Liturgy and Discipline, occasion'd the late Civil War:</hi> And is not this clear by <hi>Rushworth</hi>'s Collections, and other Protestant Historians of those times? Fourthly, the <hi>New Test</hi> objects, <hi>that the Church of</hi> England <hi>set up the Lady</hi> Jane <hi>in opposition to Q</hi> M. <hi>the Lawful Heiress to the Crown,</hi> and is not this also testisy'd by Doctor <hi>Heylin,</hi> and other Writers of those times? Fifthly, the <hi>New Test</hi> says, that <hi>Q</hi> Eliz. <hi>was a B—d,</hi> (though some what unmanerly in the expression,) and doth not an Act of Parliament (the sole Creation of the Church of <hi>England,</hi>) as another (for ought I know may annihilate it,) still unrepeal'd, witness this? Sixthly, The <hi>New Test</hi> object, <hi>that the Protestants maintain the Title of the B—d Q</hi> E. (<hi>as a prop to their Church of</hi> England) <hi>in opposition to the Lawful Title of Q.</hi> M. <hi>of</hi> Scotland, <hi>whom</hi> (<hi>after they had forc'd her to renounce her Title to the Crown, during the life of Q<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, they barbarously Murder'd her, because a Papist;</hi> And is not this also evident by the Histories of those times, as also the Speeches of the Dean of <hi>Peterborough</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Kent,</hi> as is before related? Seventhly, The <hi>New Test</hi> again objects, <q>the making those Sanguinary Laws, and that senseless Atheistical <hi>Test,</hi> whereby Gods Priests (as often as the Church of <hi>England</hi> shall think fit for their diversion) are inhumanely Massacred, and the King depriv'd of the service of the best of his friends;</q> and do not the Acts of Parliament (as yet un-repeal'd) also witness this too: Again, this <hi>Test</hi> objects, <q>that <hi>Transubstantiation</hi> being a probable opinion at least, as held by so many Learned Men, throughout the whole world, it would be a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94172:8"/>great temerity in any Man to swear there is no such thing, and is there any rational man who thinks it not so;</q> neither will the scribling Author of the Second <hi>Answer</hi> page the 9th. (by saying the same Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument runs for <hi>Mahometism,</hi>) evince the contrary, or ever pass for so much as for a probable opinion.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>my Lord,</hi> your Lordship sees I have consider'd the most material Passages of these silly Papers, not being able to guess why the <hi>New Test</hi> should occasion so much heat in the Church of <hi>Englands</hi> Party, against poor innocent Dissenters, unless coming out presently after his Majesties Gracious Declaration for <hi>Liberty of Conscience,</hi> which hath par'd their nails; that they should not hurt their neighbours, and put the rest of mankind (of his Majesties Dominions, on the same level with the Church of <hi>England</hi>) and this my Lord, I apprehend is the only reason of this great heat of theirs, and I see as little reason why that in-offensive <hi>Test,</hi> (undeniable in matter of Fact, should pass so severe a Censure of the Grand Jury of the Borough of <hi>Southwark,</hi> and these two scurrilous Answers (with that of Mrs. <hi>James</hi>) should pass unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded; but wonderful are the influences of prejudice and passion; (especially when rais'd some what more than ordinary with good Vict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals and good Wine;) but that I may free this Gent. from the suspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any ill design, the Author of this <hi>New Test</hi> had, in speaking so plainly, I do here declare, I should renounce my Religion to morrow, if I thought the principles of it could influence his Majesty to break his word (so solemnly given) to the Church of <hi>England</hi> for Protection of them, although the Catholicks are commonly traduc'd, that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the principles of their Religion, Faith is not to be kept with Hereticks, which if I thought so, I swear before the Almighty God, should rather turn Mahometan than be of it: So on the other side, the Church of <hi>Englands</hi> Religion (having found so much dis-inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity in their Writings) should be the last (of all the Sects of Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity) should God (whether for my own Sins, or the Sins of my fore-Fathers, (permit me to Apostatise from his true Faith) I should ever embrace. Nay rather, <hi>anima mea sit cum Philosophis;</hi> (as indeed more rationally,) and this I vow by the living God. Thus my Lord, having comply'd with your Lordships Commands, I submit my sense of these three Papers (as my self) to your Lordships most judicious Censure, and Subscribe my self as (in all duty, <hi>My Lord,</hi> your Lordships most humble, and (eternally) oblig'd Servant,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Philalethes</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:94172:9"/>
            <head>POSTCRIPT</head>
            <p>SInce this <hi>Reply</hi> came to the Press, the Author understood another thing called an <hi>Answer,</hi> hath been freely Published; But finding it contains nothing material more than what was in the Two former; (except the Letter of Secretary <hi>Walsingham,</hi> whose Integrity and honesty being Calculated to those times,) he thinks this <hi>Answer</hi> may also sufficiently serve for That, or any thing else they can pretend to for an <hi>Answer</hi> to the <hi>New Test,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>July 2d. 1687.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>